A Guide to the Noel Behn papers M1084
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Noel Behn papers
>circa 1950-1998
M1084
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
93.0 Linear feet (183 manuscript boxes, 1 carton, 2 flat boxes)
The papers feature the materials from Noel Behn's career as an author and a producer; and, include manuscripts (by him and other authors), personal notebooks, appointment books, research materials (clippings, magazines, printouts, off-prints, related to Hauptman-Lindbergh case and other famous criminal cases, and books by other authors, heavily annotated), annotated texts and proofs, actors' portfolios, Writers' Guild of America documents, legal and financial papers, and Correspondence.
Behn, Noel
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to Stanford University, Special Collections by Tom Fontana, executor of the estate of Noel Behn, in 1999.
Access
Unrestricted. Except that: "Hauptmann Case Films" (May 1936) are badly damaged and are awaiting conservation; The Fra (not for mummies): A Journal of Affirmation (Vol. 2, Oct. 1908 - March 1909) has been transferred to the Rare Book Collection.
Arrangement
Series I. Personal papers
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Writings by Noel Behn
Series IV. General files
Series V. Video and audio materials
Series VI. Works by others
Series VII. Clippings and magazines
Separated Materials note
The collection contained originally "Hauptman Case Films" (May, 1936), now in conservation; "The Fra (not for mummies). A Journal of Affirmation," Volume 2, Oct. 1908-March 1909, now in Rare Books; a comprehensive collection of Noel Behn's published works in various editions and translations, as well as books by other authors (most of the books went to the Green library stacks).
Biography
Noel Behn was a novelist, screenwriter, theatrical producer, and actor who spent his whole creative life in Manhattan. A graduate of Stanford University, class of 1950, Behn was active in the New York Theater Community for more than 50 years as the producing director of the Cherry Lane Theater, a pioneer of the off Broadway theater movement. Among the influential works premiered there under his direction were Sean O’Casey’s "Purple Dust" and Samuel Beckett’s "Endgame". His first novel, The Kremlin Letter (1966), based on his experiences in the United States Counterintelligence Corps, was made into a popular film by John Huston in 1970 which starred Orson Welles. He later wrote The Big Stick-up at Brink’s (1977), a nonfiction account of the 1950 Brink’s Robbery in Boston, subsequently made into the film The Brink’s Job. In 1991 Noel Behn was hired as a consultant for the popular TV series, Homocide: Life on the Street, for which he periodically wrote scripts. His latest book, Lindbergh: The Crime (1994) is currently being developed as a feature film.
Fontana, Tom; American literature
- PERSONAL PAPERS
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains biographical, legal, medical, financial documents and data, awards.
  - Correspondence, bills, property documents, receipts, postcards, statements, contracts, computer materials, etc, primarily 1980s. (Box 4)
  - Bills, statements, medical info, various financial documents, agreements, "OUST" papers, "Musical Theatre Academy of New York" papers, "Musical Tent" papers, "Fosse Fellowships" papers; “Writers' Guild of America - 41st Annual Awards", 1989; miscellaneous clippings, etc. (Box 12)
  - Bankruptcy materials (1980s), High Fidelity Recordings, Inc. papers, Actors' Equity Association papers, address and notebooks, "Chronology of Aphra Behn's life", miscellaneous financial documents, notes, personal papers. (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous papers (mostly medical and financial: bills, taxes, loans etc.), 80s-90s, no date. (Box 57)
  - Medical info and booklets, medical records, Writers' Guild Association paperwork, bills, miscellaneous receipts, legal documents, etc. (Box 72)
  - Daily reminders and diaries, 1986-1990, 1995; miscellaneous memos, receipts, etc. (Box 136)
  - Telephone, address and appointments books, diaries, daily reminders with notes, enclosures etc., some half or less filled; 1992-1994, no date. (Box 140)
  - Diaries, organizers, address books, daily reminders; 1968, 1970, 1973, 1975-1977, 1980, 1981, no date. (Box 141)
  - Diaries, daily reminders, to-do lists, financial documents (receipts etc.), miscellaneous; 1982-1985, 1987, 1996-1998, no date. (Box 142)
  - Monthly statements, paid bills, pay charts, credit ratings, receipts, tax documents, calendars and to-do lists, etc.; 1987-88, miscellaneous dates, no date. (Box 157)
  - Dorothy Behn's (Noel Behn's mother) living will; Writers Guild Health Plan; address and phone books and a diary; miscellaneous receipts; banking, household, phone, automobile and other living expenses, miscellaneous; 1960s - 1990s. (Box 171)
  - Medical information, miscellaneous receipts, recorded expenses, tickets, bank records, invoices, personal papers and documents, among them Noel Behn's U.S. passport and his Army record; miscellaneous dates. (Box 184)
- CORRESPONDENCE
  - Miscellaneous business and personal correspondence, including fan letters. (Box 39)
  - Miscellaneous official, business, and personal correspondence (letters, postcards, telegrams, notes), including a photocopy of John Edgar Hoover letter to Washington Post (Feb. 6, 1967), a letter from Mrs. Elizabeth Cane regarding Lindbergh case (1997), etc. (Box 133)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence; incl. fan mail and Christmas cards (1991, 1993, 1997 files), letters from editors, Owen Laster and Maria Bello letters regarding Cindy Wirth's business activities, etc. (Box 173)
  - Business correspondence, 1980s; a letter from FBI, Jan. 2, 1979; a letter to Mr. Anton Mueller, Editor, Grove and Atlantic Press, by a man claiming to be the kidnapped Lindbergh's son, Feb. 9, 1994; miscellaneous postcards, notes, etc. (Box 185)
- WRITING
  This series contains manuscripts, proofs, drafts, etc. written by Noel Behn or co-authored.
  - Hauptman Case materials, 1930s: correspondence, document index, various photocopies, investigation files, reports and related materials; includes files 1-140 out of 243 (presumably the materials for the book "Lindbergh: The Crime", 1994). (Box 1)
  - Hauptman Case materials, 1930s: correspondence, document index, various photocopies, investigation files, reports, clippings and related materials; includes files 234-243A; materials related to the film "The Brink's Job"; preliminary drafts and story ideas; "Seven Silent Men" materials; correspondence, various photocopies, typescripts and fragments of typescripts, clippings, contracts, miscellaneous. (Box 3)
  - Hauptman Case materials, 1930s: correspondence, document index, various photocopies, investigation files, reports, clippings and related materials; includes files 141-230. (Box 2)
  - "Seven Silent Men" materials, continued: typescripts and fragments of typescripts, 1983. (Box 5)
  - "Seven Silent Men" materials, continued; unidentified fragments, typescripts and fragments of typescripts, 1983-1984, no date; an annotated uncorrected proof of "Seven Silent Men" and a typewritten final draft of "Homicide: Life on the Street" (episode 2, August 3, 1993). (Box 6)
  - "Greybull" (A Part of "Seven Silent Men") materials; "Story Segments from Untitled Novel" (1990); "Hallelujah: A Novel in Progress"; "Calcutta" fragment; "Kootch"; "Fatal Beauty" (A Screenplay by Behn from the novel by John Godey); typescripts and fragments of typescripts, Feb. 10, 1986 - March 10, 1986. (Box 7)
  - "Fatal Beauty" materials (continued): original 7/18/1985 corrected copy, 7/17/1985 uncorrected copy, fragments of final copy; old undated copy; July 1 – Dec. 1985 copies; "Master", Feb. 4, 1986, typescripts. (Box 8)
  - "Master", no date; "G-Series to W-Series" [?], no date; "Lemonade Set-Ups", no date; "Homicide: Life on the Street", episode 2, "Black and Blue", 7/28/1993, and episode 1, 06/04/1999; "Seven Silent Men", typescripts and a manuscript, 11/4/1987; "CLOUT!" (by Tom Fantana and Noel Behn), July 5, 1989 (based on Behn's "Seven Silent", typescript. (Box 9)
  - "Seven Silent Men" (play), drafts and fragments, Aug. 4, 1987, outline, April 27, 1987; other "Seven Silent Men" materials, no date; "Clout!", July 5, 1989; "DELL - 2 plus 2" and "Tulip Time Bang" draft, 7/6/1997; "The Tea Party" and other unidentified fragments, no date; "The World Dies" fragments, typescripts and manual drafts. (Box 10)
  - Unidentified typescript with a foreword by George Burus; unidentified fragments; "Seven Silent Men" materials: outline, chronology, research, early notes, typewritten and handwritten fragments, miscellaneous. (Box 13)
  - "Seven Silent Men" materials (continued): outline, chronology, research, early notes, typewritten and handwritten fragments, miscellaneous. (Box 18)
  - "Seven Silent Men" materials (continued): outline, chronology, research, early notes, typewritten and handwritten fragments, miscellaneous; Homicide materials, 1999: drafts, class '99; unidentified fragments; "Not So Lucky Lindy" mini-series outline, Jan 20, 1995; "Homicide, episode no. 307", 5/17/1994: typescripts, research materials. (Box 19)
  - "Three to Tango", 6/5/94; "High Command" and other fragments, no date; "Jody Boy", 5/95; "Homicide", casting; "Elaine" materials; "Homicide on Net - Program Breakdown" materials, 1996; "Seven Silent Men" materials; "The Debriefing", "JESSUP" materials; unidentified typescripts, fragments; random notes, etc. (Box 20)
  - "Pardue Brothers" case materials: FBI materials (copies), 1969-1987; "Pardue / Osgood / Featherson" materials: typescripts and fragments of typescripts, 1985, no date; FBI-N.Behn correspondence, 1980s. (Box 23)
  - "Pardue Brothers" case materials (continued): typescripts; Hauptmann / Lindbergh case materials; typescripts, correspondence; "Quick" (screenplay), no date. (Box 24)
  - "Fatal Beauty" (screenplay by N. Behn from the novel by John Godeg), Feb 10, 1986 (typescripts); "Clout!" by Tom Fontana and N. Behn, based on the novel by N. Behn, July 5, 1989 (typescripts); "Good Cop / Bad Cop" (teleplay by N. Behn and Tom Fontana from the story by John Tinker and Bruce Paltrow), Sept 12-Dec 3, 1991, no date (typescripts and fragments); "Greybull" materials (typewritten fragments, clippings). (Box 25)
  - "Ping Pong" materials: typescripts and fragments, miscellaneous drafts; unidentified typewritten fragments; no date. (Box 27)
  - "Ping Pong" materials (continued): typescripts and drafts, research materials (clippings, miscellaneous). (Box 28)
  - "Ping Pong" materials (continued): typescripts and fragments of typescripts. (Box 29)
  - "Ping Pong" materials (continued): typescripts and fragments, miscellaneous worksheets; "Masters" and "Yellows" materials (belong to "Seven Silent Men"), typewritten fragments. (Box 30)
  - "Yellows" materials (continued); "Extras" (including any revised versions); no date. (Box 31)
  - "Extras" (continued); The Brink's Job materials (typewritten). (Box 32)
  - "The Brink's Job" materials (continued); "Daybreak at Dying Elk" ("Master"); "Magazine" materials, typewritten; "Catherine's First Tale" (handwritten and typewritten drafts); "A Minor Matter of Retribution" (typescript); outline for "Contacts" (typewritten); "The Treasure of Berlin" (typewritten); no date; "A Present from Your Old Man" (annotated, fragile typewritten copies). (Box 33)
  - "A Present from Your Old Man" (a typescript), no date; "Seven Silent Men": early drafts, extra copies, early chapters (typescripts, fragments of typescripts). (Box 34)
  - "Seven Silent Men" materials (continued): early drafts, extra copies, early chapters (typescripts, fragments of typescripts). (Box 35)
  - "Seven Silent Men" materials (continued): early drafts, extra copies, early chapters (typescripts, fragments of typescripts), miscellaneous cards and notes; "The Shining Man" typescript, 1990. (Box 36)
  - "The Shining Man" (continued); "Seven Silent Men" - "Out Yellow" (typescripts, fragments of typescripts); unidentified fragments, no date. (Box 37)
  - "Seven Silent Men" - "Out Yellows" materials (typescripts and fragments); miscellaneous fragments. Some folders are empty. (Box 42)
  - "Seven Silent Men" - "Out Yellows" (continued); notes on Lindbergh case (typewritten). (Box 43)
  - "Seven Silent Men" - "Out Yellows" (continued); "Lindbergh: The Crime" (galleys, fragments of galleys, related correspondence and other materials), 1993. (Box 44)
  - "Lindbergh: The Crime" (continued); "Seven Silent Men - original, final manuscript" (typewritten, annotated), 1983; "A Continuing Untitled Work in Progress", 1991; miscellaneous drafts, fragments, and notes, no date. (Box 45)
  - "Lindbergh: The Crime" (fragments); "Seven Silent Men" (typewritten drafts, outlines, fragments, etc.), 1987, no date; miscellaneous fragments, typewritten, 1987, no date. (Box 46)
  - "Seven Silent Men", Aug. 4, 1987; "Crime Without Passion"; "The Onion Patch", "Love Slave", "Berin" [?], "Breakdown of Action" and other unidentified typewritten fragments and handwritten notes, most likely by N. Behn; "Tattingers" materials (some in co-authorship with Tom Fontana; typescripts, notes, fragments etc., 1988 mostly. (Box 47)
  - "Tattinger's" materials (drafts, notes, research materials); miscellaneous fragments; "Seven Silent Men", book 2 (an annotated typescript). (Box 50)
  - "Seven Silent Men," annotated typewritten fragments (mostly disorganized) and handwritten notes. (Box 51)
  - "Seven Silent Men," ibid.; Lindbergh case materials ("A Third Suspect" typescripts, "Countdown"). (Box 52)
  - "Lindbergh: The Crime" (a typescript), other Lindbergh case materials ("Countdown," "Book Three: A 3rd Suspect," "What of Elizabeth?" - typescripts). (Box 53)
  - "A Third Suspect: The Lindbergh Kidnapping Revisited" (a typescript); "Book Three: A Third Suspect" (a typescript); Lindbergh materials (outlines, scripts, etc.); "Fatal Beauty," a screenplay from the novel by John Godey (a typescript); a copy of "Fatal Beauty" by John Godey with Behn's marks. (Box 54)
  - "Fatal Beauty" materials (typescripts, synopses, outlines, etc.); "Seven Silent Men" materials. (Box 59)
  - Typescripts and fragments ("Clout!" and "Tattinger's," episode 7, both in co-authorship with Tom Fontana; "Koniker", "The Morrows", "Net of Treason," miscellaneous fragments). Incl. also editors' notes and N. Behn's answers, typewritten. 1988-1989, no date. (Box 66)
  - "Shining Man" and "Ping-Pong" typescripts (some are annotated); editor's notes; unidentified typewritten and handwritten fragments; Lindbergh case materials (photocopies of 1930s memos, investigation reports, clippings, etc.). (Box 67)
  - Lindbergh case materials (continued): photocopies of 1930s memos, investigation reports, clippings, etc.; Governor Hoffman's dossier (mostly photocopies); N. Behn's edit of Joe Fox's edit (an annotated typescript) of "The Shining Man"[?]. (Box 68)
  - "Lindbergh. A Crime Revisited" and other Lindbergh-related typescripts; "Ping-Pong" (fragments, typewritten); "Voyage of Tsars", typewritten; an untitled typescript; no date. (Box 69)
  - "Ping-Pong" background research materials, presentation papers etc. (including off prints, clippings, booklets); old stories and scripts ("You are right", "Paris stories" etc.), "A Present from Your Old Man" (typewritten). 1960s-1980s, no date. (Box 71)
  - "The Great Brinks Robbery" typescripts; "Hauptmann-Lindbergh Case" materials (continued to materials in boxes 1-3, files 300-334A). (Box 74)
  - "Hauptmann-Lindbergh" files, 334B-371. (Box 75)
  - "Lindbergh. The Crime" typescripts and notes; "Ping Pong" research materials (newsletters, reports and copies of reports on world population, biological and chemical weapons, travel, etc.); miscellaneous materials, drafts and notes. (Box 77)
  - "Lindbergh. The Crime" typescript; "Quick" (screenplay, annotated typescript); an address book and a notebook related to "Ping Pong" research. (Box 78)
  - "The Shining Man"; "Winter Term" in co-authorship with David Black and Tom Fontana; "Story Segments from Untitled Novel", "The Cherry Lane" (typescripts); "Lindbergh" research materials, miscellaneous. (Box 81)
  - "High Command" (typescripts, fragments, research materials); "Tromsa" (ibid.); "Lindbergh Movie Outline" file (typescripts, fragments, research materials, miscellaneous); "Lindbergh Misc." file; "Homic[ide] personnel info" file. (Box 83)
  - "Homicide No. 614" files, "Della Ventura" file, "Fort Halabird" file (typescripts and drafts, photocopies of clippings, research materials, faxes, miscellaneous). (Box 84)
  - "Story Segments from Untitled Novel"; "A Previously Untitled Work in Progress"; "Catch-Up" (in co-authorship with David Black and Tom Fontana), 5 versions; "EK Rebut" and "The Summary"; "4th Station, 1st rough [draft]"; "Chapter Two-A and Chapter Two-B"; unidentified fragments and notes. Typescripts mostly, 1988-1991, no date. (Box 85)
  - "Halj" file; "Ping Pong" materials (two copies); "The Devil's Tongue" typescript; typewritten unidentified fragments; a notebook; miscellaneous handwritten notes (possible "Clout" notes). (Box 86)
  - "Seven Silent Men," various versions, 8/4/1987-6/26/1989. Typescripts and fragments of typescripts, mostly annotated. (Box 91)
  - "FBI File 300" - Lindbergh case materials, 1930s (mostly photocopies of reports, protocols etc.); "Score!," "Seven Silent Men" (typescripts and photocopies of typescripts, mostly annotated), 1980s, no date. (Box 92)
  - "Seven Silent Men": 1st Pass Galleys, Books I-IV with Don Fine's changes to it (typescripts and photocopies of typescripts, annotate); 9/1/1983; no date. (Box 93)
  - "Seven Silent Men": 1st Pass of Galleys, 9/1/1983; Xerox of Master Copy, Books I-IV, no date; miscellaneous fragments (typescripts and photocopies of typescripts, annotated). (Box 94)
  - "Seven Silent Men" materials (photocopies, typescripts, fragments of typescripts, outlines, summaries, memos, promo materials, related correspondence, an editor's notes, etc.); 1980s, no date; includes also "Lindbergh: The Crime" materials: "Lindbergh's Way: The Third Investigation" original (typescript); "A Third Suspect. The Lindbergh Kidnapping Revisited", proof copy (typewritten), fragments; no date. (Box 95)
  - "Lindbergh's Way. The First Investigation", "War of the Lawmen. The Second Investigation," "A Family Secret? The Third Investigation" (a typescript); "Lindbergh's Investigation" (an incomplete typescript); "A Third Suspect. The Lindbergh Kidnapping Revisited" (a typescript); fragments. No date. (Box 96)
  - "Homicide" episodes (typescripts, annotated and not annotated), "Dellaventura"; 1990s, no date. (Box 100)
  - "Homicide" episodes: "Class of '99" (miscellaneous typewritten fragments, notes, revisions etc.), "Mother's Day" (typewritten), "Dellaventura" drafts, "Saved", "Homicide" miscellaneous; 1994-1997, no date. (Box 105)
  - "Silent Service", "Silent Sphynx", "Halj", "Lindbergh. The Crime" (typescripts and fragments of typescripts, some annotated), 1993, 1995, 1997, no date. (Box 107)
  - "Lindbergh. The Crime", "Book Three. House of Cards", typescripts; no date. (Box 108)
  - "Quick", "Seven Silent Men" (typescripts and fragments of typescripts, some annotated); no date. (Box 109)
  - Untitled typescript (possibly a photocopy of a typescript), chapters 65-85, no date.; "Book Three. House of Cards", no date; "Book Three (Seventeen)", no date; "Homicide" (episode two: "A ghost of a Chance"), teleplay by N. Behn, story by Tom Fontana, Sept. 3, 1992. (Some typescripts are annotated.) (Box 110)
  - "Homicide" episodes, "Split Image" (in a co-authorship with Siv Svendsen); typescripts and fragments of typescripts, some annotated; 1991-1993, no date. (Box 115)
  - "Lindbergh. A Crime Revisited" (unedited); "Split Image. A Screenplay" (in a co-authorship with Siv Svendsen); "Kootch", fragments (most likely by N. Behn) - typescripts and fragments of typescripts, Nov. 1-15, 1991; no date. (Box 116)
  - "Split Image", "Flashback" (screenplays in a co-authorship with Siv Svendsen), typewritten fragments, 1991, no date. (Box 117)
  - "Lindbergh. A Crime Revisited" (unedited); "Quick" (a typescript and fragments); 7/15/90, no date. (Box 118)
  - "Quick" (fragments), "Lindbergh" drafts (typewritten); no date. (Box 121)
  - "Lindbergh" typescripts and editors' notes; June 6, 1993, no date. (Box 122)
  - "Lindbergh" typescripts, "EM Series" fragments, no date. (Box 123)
  - "EM Series" fragments, "Dellaventura" drafts, "Smiling Men" materials, Lindbergh case materials, "Halj" outpages, miscellaneous fragments (typescripts, some heavily annotated; Web printouts; miscellaneous); 1976; 1990s; no date. (Box 125)
  - Incl. books that are research materials, with marks, bookmarks, attached notes etc. (some are damaged): 1) Lindbergh. A biography by Leonard Mosley ("Doubleday and Company, Inc.", NY, 1976); 2) The Day the Bubble Burst by Gordon Thomas and Max Morgan-Witts (same publisher, 1979); 3) FBI. An Uncensored Look Behind The Walls by Sanford J. Ungar ("Little, Brown and Company", 1975); 4) The Trial of Bruno Richard Hauptmann by Sidney B. Whipple ("Country Life Press", Garden City, N.Y., 1937); 5) 1929. America before the Crash by Warren Sloat ("Macmillan Publishing Co., Inc.", N.Y., 1979); 6) A Year on the Killing Streets. Homicide by David Simon (Houghton Mifflin Company, Boston, 1991); 7) Kidnap. The Story of the Lindbergh Case by George Waller ("The Dual Press", N.Y., 1961). (Box 126)
  - "The Devil's Tongue", "Homicide-NB / 410", "A Present from Your Old Man", "Night Owls", outlines, fragments, story ideas etc. (typescripts, some annotated; handwritten notes). No date. (Box 132)
  - "Seven Silent Men", "Little Girl - Master", no date; "The Brinks Robbery" (rewritten starting 2/27/73); "Homicide", Episode Two, "The Ghost of a Chance", Aug. 27, 1992 (typescripts and photocopies of typescripts). (Box 134)
  - "The Great Brinks Robbery", "Tarzan of the Tetons", fragments (typescripts, photocopies of typescripts; some annotated); no date. (Box 137)
  - "Sihler", "Act of Treason", "The Shadow Boxer", "Mother Luv" fragments, "Ping Pong" and "Lindbergh" materials, untitled fragments (typescripts, photocopies of typescripts, fragments, etc.), 1997, no date. (Box 138)
  - Lindbergh case research materials (photocopies of documents, clippings, etc.), Behn's drafts (typewritten and handwritten), notes, etc.; includes also typewritten fragments of an untitled manuscript. 1980s mostly; no date. (Box 139)
  - Lindbergh case - research materials (mostly photocopies of documents); "Ping Pong", "Brink's!" (typescripts, with some notes and corrections); no date. (Box 144)
  - "Seven Silent Men" (typescripts and fragments, edited); Lindbergh case materials (mostly photocopies of clippings and other documents regarding Elizabeth Morrow and Marrow family), miscellaneous dates. (Box 145)
  - "Ping Pong" fragments; untitled fragments edited by Joe Fox; typescripts, no date; some annotated. Includes also Lindbergh case materials, mostly photocopies of miscellaneous documents regarding Morrow family; miscellaneous dates. (Box 147)
  - "Devil's Tongue" (typescripts, fragments); untitled fragments, no date. (Box 148)
  - "Seven Silent Men" (typescripts, scene reports, outlines), "Black Box" (typescripts), miscellaneous and untitled typescripts and fragments of typescripts. June 23, 1987; no date. (Box 150)
  - "Jennifer-Yellows", no date; "Subject to Change" ("3d suspect"), in co-authorship with Siv Svendsen, April 12, 1991; July 30, 1991; no date (typescripts, a tear sheet, off prints). (Box 151)